Guide to the Journal of Experimental Zoology Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Journal of Experimental Zoology records
1891-1964
MS 1098
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.25
The records include correspondence, financial papers, minutes, and miscellanea relating to the publication and operation of the Journal of Experimental Zoology. Correspondence with editorial board members, contributors, and members of the Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology document the daily activities of the journal's staff. Correspondents include; Edwin Grant Conklin, Jacques Loeb, Charles Rupert Stockard, Ross Granville Harrison, and John Spangler Nicholas.
Journal of Experimental Zoology
American Society of Zoologists
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Department of Zoology, Yale University, 1966; and transferred from the John Spangler Nicholas Papers (MS 929), 1984.
Associated Materials
Associated material: John Spangler Nicholas Papers (MS 929), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.)
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, 1894-1964. II. Office Files, 1891-1947.
Biographical / Historical
The Journal of Experimental Zoology was founded in 1904 by Ross Granville Harrison, Merkel H. Jacobs, and others in Baltimore, Maryland. A private corporation was formed and was responsible for the publication until December, 1932, when the corporation was dissolved and the journal came under the supervision of the Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The journal was printed in Baltimore from 1904 to 1908 at Williams and Wilkins Company, and from 1908 to the present by the Wistar Institute.
Scope and Contents
The records include correspondence, financial papers, minutes, and miscellanea relating to the publication and operation of the Journal of Experimental Zoology. Correspondence with editorial board members, contributors, and members of the Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology document the daily activities of the journal's staff. Correspondents include; Edwin Grant Conklin, Jacques Loeb, Charles Rupert Stockard, Ross Granville Harrison, and John Spangler Nicholas.
Other Finding Aids
For an index of manuscripts in this collection and their authors, and for a listing of correspondence, please consult the Collection Inventory.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Journal of Experimental Zoology; Journalism; Science; Zoology -- Research; Zoology -- Periodicals; Zoology; Castle, William E. (William Ernest), 1867-1962; Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952; Davenport, Charles Benedict, 1866-1944; Harrison, Ross G. (Ross Granville), 1870-1959; Jacobs, M. H. (Merkel Henry), 1884-1974; Jennings, H. S. (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947; Knower, Henry McElderry, 1868-; Lillie, Frank Rattray, 1870-1947; Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945; Nicholas, John Spangler, 1893-; Parker, George Howard, 1864-1955; Pearl, Raymond, 1879-1940; Stockard, Charles R. (Charles Rupert), 1879-1939; Wilson, Edmund B. (Edmund Beecher), 1856-1939; Williams & Wilkins; Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology; Yale University
- Correspondence, 1894-1964; Series I; 9.5 linear feet (23 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in five sections: General, Select, Editorial Board, Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology, and Manuscripts.
  - General, 1903-1944, 1955-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Select
    - Collaborators, 1903-1907 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Continental Trust Company, Maryland Trust Company, 1913-1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1928-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - National Science Foundation, 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Pine, John B., 1901-1924 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - Rotograph Company, 1906-1908 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Williams & Wilkins Company, 1904-1909, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Editorial Board
    - General, 1903-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    - General, 1946-1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Castle, William Ernest, 1904-1934 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1903-1937, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
    - Davenport, Charles Benedict, 1903-1934 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Jacobs, Merkel H., 1927-1936 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Jennings, Herbert Spencer, 1904-1935 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
    - Lillie, Frank Rattray, 1905-1935, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
    - Loeb, Jacques, 1904-1924 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1903-1945 (Box 4, Folder 30-33)
    - Parker, George Howard, 1904-1934, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 34-35)
    - Pearl, Raymond, 1913-1935 (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
    - Stockard, Charles Rupert, 1920-1934 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Wilson, Edmund Beecher, 1903-1933 (Box 5, Folder 39-40)
  - Wistar Institute of Anatomy and Biology
    - Farris, Edmond J., 1937-1947 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Greenman, Milton J., 1907-1937 (Box 6, Folder 42-45)
    - Advisory Board, miscellaneous, 1894, 1898, 1910-1937 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Advisory Board, miscellaneous, 1938-1942, 1945-1948, 1955-1964 (Box 7, Folder 47-48)
    - Finance Committee, Publications Board, 1908-1945 (Box 7, Folder 49-50)
    - Correspondence re: manuscripts
      - 1908-1915 (Box 7, Folder 51-53)
      - 1916-1931 (Box 8, Folder 54-59)
      - 1932-1943 (Box 9, Folder 60-66)
      - 1944-1963 (Box 10, Folder 67-74)
  - Manuscripts
    - 1904-1911 (Box 11, Folder 75-82)
    - 1912-1919 (Box 12, Folder 83-90)
    - 1920-1925 (Box 13, Folder 91-96)
    - 1925-1935 (Box 14, Folder 97-104)
    - 1936-1939 (Box 15, Folder 105-111)
    - 1939-1941 (Box 16, Folder 112-117)
    - 1941-1964, undated (Box 17, Folder 118-124)
    - Nos. 864, 918-919, 1021-1175, [ca.1942-1946] (Box 18, Folder 125-132)
    - Nos. 1176-1375, [ca.1944-1948] (Box 19, Folder 133-140)
    - Nos. 1376-1685, [ca.1948-1953] (Box 20, Folder 141-148)
    - Nos. 1686-1915, [ca.1952-1956] (Box 21, Folder 149-156)
    - Nos. 1916-1985, 2003-2043, 2099-2280, [ca.1954-1961] (Box 22, Folder 157-165)
    - Nos. 2282-2383, 2405-2699, miscellaneous, [ca.1958-1964] (Box 23, Folder 166-173)
- Office Files, 1891-1947; Series II; 1.75 linear feet (5 boxes, 1 folio)
  This series is arranged in four sections: Financial records, Minutes of stockholders' meetings, Record of manuscripts, and Miscellanea.
  - Financial records
    - Cash book, 1903-1932 (Box 24, Folder 174)
    - Ledger, 1904-1908 (Box 24, Folder 175)
    - Stock and transfer book, 1904 (Box 24, Folder 176)
    - Financial statements, 1904-1908, 1913, 1921-1931 (Box 24, Folder 177-178)
    - Papers re: investments, 1908, 1921-1930, undated (Box 24, Folder 179)
    - Bills and receipts: A-Z, [ca.1904-1908, 1930-1947] (Box 25, Folder 180-182)
    - Checks, 1904-1930 (Box 25, Folder 183)
    - Checkbooks, 1904-1947, undated (Box 25, Folder 184)
    - Bank book, 1904-1922 (Box 25, Folder 184)
    - Bank statements, 1922-1947 (Box 25, Folder 185-186)
    - Tax forms
      - Federal income tax, 1914-1919 (Box 25, Folder 187)
      - New York State tax, 1919-1932 (Box 25, Folder 188)
      - Capital stock tax, 1918-1926 (Box 25, Folder 189)
  - Minutes of stockholders' meetings, 1904-1932 (Box 26, Folder 190-191)
  - Record of manuscripts
    - Nos. 1-294, 1904-1913 (Box 26, Folder 192)
    - Nos. 564-983, 1918-1927 (Box 26A, Folder 193)
    - Nos. 1-251, 1928-1932 (Box 26A, Folder 193)
  - Miscellanea
    - Legal papers, 1904, 1932 (Box 27, Folder 194)
    - Announcements and advertisements, 1903-1904, 1945 (Box 27, Folder 195)
    - Subscription campaign, 1904-1905 (Box 27, Folder 196)
    - Subscription lists, 1904-1913 (Box 27, Folder 197)
    - Mailing lists, 1902-1911, undated (Box 27, Folder 198-201)
    - Inventories, miscellaneous statistics, 1907, undated (Box 27, Folder 202)
    - Instructions for secretary, authors, 1904-1933, undated (Box 27, Folder 203)
    - Stationery and forms, undated (Box 27, Folder 204)
    - Knower, Henry McElderry: photographs of Jamaica, [ca.1891-1895] (Box 28, Folder 205-207)